本劇改編自聖經  將始終盡力保持《聖經》真諦
某些場景含暴力鏡頭  請觀眾自行斟酌
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
人為的過失導致了大洪水
Human failings led to the great flood.
錯誤的選擇   錯誤的決定
Wrong choices, wrong decisions.
諾亞後，一個新的開始
After Noah, a new beginning...
和給亞伯拉罕的應許
and a promise for Abraham.
上帝對我說話我了
God has spoken to me.
他將帶領我們到一個新的家園
He will lead us to a new home.
他應許要給我如天上繁星般多的後裔
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
幫助以色列人實現應許
To help the Israelites fulfil the promise,
上帝差遣摩西 使他們擺脫奴役
God sent Moses to free them from slavery.
主
Lord!
約書亞帶領他們進入應許之地
Joshua led them into the promised land.
耶利哥是我們的
Jericho is ours!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
但以色列人面臨著來自
But the Israelites faced brutal opposition...
非利士人殘酷的抵抗
from the Philistines.
即使有些人敢於抵抗
Some dared to fight back.
但甚至參孫也不可能戰勝他們
But not even Samson could overcome them.
先知撒母耳動員以色列人以上帝之名團結一致
The prophet Samuel led the Israelites in God's name,
但人們希望更多的人
but the people wanted more...
來帶領他們的戰鬥
someone to lead them in battle.
那你們想怎麼樣   一位王
- What do you want? - A king.
王  這些王總變成暴君
A king? They become tyrants.
由上帝選中的王不會這樣
Not if they are chosen by God.
掃羅  我膏你作以色列的第一位王
Saul, I anoint you the first king of Israel.
我想，作為神的先知
May I, as God's prophet,
我可以盡我所能幫助你
help you in any way I can.
但誰夠好來治理上帝的國度？
But is any man good enough to rule God's kingdom?
《聖經》
第04集-國度
都準備好了？
Are the men ready?
他們準備好了
They're ready.
撒母耳在哪裡
Where is Samuel?
他應該在這裡
He should be here.
我們必須在我們開戰前獻祭
We must make a sacrifice before we attack.
我們不能再等了
We cannot wait any longer.
掃羅  願上帝饒恕你
Saul! May God forgive you!
撒母耳
Samuel.
你在這幾天在哪裡
Where were you?
我們已經等待了七天   七天
Seven days we have waited. Seven days.
我的人都要放棄了
My men are deserting.
好好當你的王。 把獻祭的事交給我
Then be a king. Leave the job of priest to me.
你認為神喜歡你這樣越權獻祭嗎？
Do you think God values your sacrifice more than mine?
撒母耳
Samuel.
上帝命令你們
God instructs you...
殺滅萬事萬物
kill everyone and everything
在以色列歷史上開始了一個新時代
A new era in Israelite history is beginning...
先知和君王的時代
the period of prophets and kings.
他們必須共同努力，以保護應許之地
They must work together to secure the promised land.
拿起武器
To arms!
勝利
Victory!
掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
上帝與我同在
God is with me!
你只有一項任務
You had one task,
上帝的一道簡單命令
one simple command from God.
摧毀一切  -我們已遵從了他的命令
- Destroy everything. - We followed his commands.
我聽到的這些羊叫聲又是怎麼回事
Then what is this bleating of goats in my ears?
牛群的低哞和羊羔的慟哭又是什麼
What is this lowing of cattle and wailing of lambs?
死的東西會哭嗎
Can the dead cry out?
這位異教徒王又是誰
And who is this pagan king?
過會兒就處死他
He is to be put to death later.
主說寬恕  你便可寬恕
When the Lord says spare, you spare.
主說殺
When he says kill...
撒母耳
Samuel!
你雖是我們的先知  但我是你的王
You are our prophet, but I am your king.
上帝所給的，祂隨時可以收回
What the Lord gives, he can take away.
這是上帝說的還是你說的
Are these God's words or yours?
你的後裔本可以統治逾千年
Your descendants could have ruled for over a thousand years.
但今天
But today,
上帝已經拋棄你了
God has forsaken you.
上帝還說了什麼
More divine words?
上帝已收回你的能力
God has torn your power from you.
他想找一個合他心意的人
He wants a man after his own heart
給我倒酒  -是的陛下
Bring me wine. Sire.
聽到沒有  快點
Do you hear me? Now!
是  陛下
Yes, sire!
也許是我太不耐煩了
Perhaps I have been hasty.
我應該祈求撒母耳的原諒
I should ask Samuel's forgiveness.
把撒母耳帶來見我
Bring Samuel to me.
他走了  陛下
He's gone, Majesty.
走了
Gone?
撒母耳
Samuel!
掃羅觸怒了上帝
After Saul's disobedience,
而今上帝指引先知撒母耳
God commands his prophet Samuel...
尋找一位新的王
to find a new king.
年輕人
Young man!
你叫什麼名字
What is your name?
大衛  先生
David, sir.
我叫大衛
My name is David.
我膏立於你  伯利恆的大衛
I anoint you, David of Bethlehem,
在掃羅死後
to be the next king of Israel...
繼任以色列王
once Saul is dead.
父親  怎麼了
Father, what's wrong?
告訴我怎麼了
Tell me what's wrong.
沒事
Nothing is wrong.
這是一場偉大的勝利
It was a great victory.
我需要休息  僅此而已
I need rest. That is all.
睡吧  睡吧
Sleep. Sleep.
主啊  寬恕你的僕人吧
Lord, forgive your servant!
後來
In time,
大衛成了掃羅的朝前侍從
David becomes an attendant in Saul's court...
一位奉侍王室的 預備王儲
a king in waiting.
非利士人的威脅持續增強
The Philistine threat continues to grow.
現在他們有了一個新的勇士
Now they have a new champion...
歌利亞
Goliath.
你們誰敢出來與我作戰
Will one of you fight me?
以色列人  你們贏了
Israelites, you win,
非利士人就做你們的奴隸
and the Philistines will be your slaves.
我贏了
I win,
你們
and you...
就做我們的奴隸
will be our slaves.
總得有人跟他作戰  -你退下  約拿單
Someone must fight him! Not you, Jonathan.
戰勝他的勇士將獲萬貫家財
The warrior who defeats him will be a rich man.
一個以色列人都不敢
Not one man in Israel?
"上帝的子民" 一個都不敢出來迎戰嗎
Not one of God's people.
我來
I'll do it.
大衛
David.
你不是士兵  你是牧羊人
You're no soldier. You're a shepherd.
是的  牧羊人
Yes, a shepherd.
正如我保護我的羊一樣  上帝也會保護我
As I protect my sheep, God will protect me.
你們的信心在哪裡
Where is your faith?
你們的上帝在哪裡
Where is your god?
我會殺了他
I will kill him.
帶上這個
You'll need this.
沒有這個更好
I'll be better without it.
我雖然行過死陰的幽谷
Yea, though I walk in the valley of the shadow of death,
也不怕遭害
I fear no evil...
只因你與我同在
for you are with me.
你的杖  你的竿
Thy rod and staff,
都安慰我
they comfort me.
你用油膏了我的頭
You anoint my head with oil.
使我的福杯滿溢
My cup over?ows.
我一生一世必有恩惠慈愛
Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me...
隨著我
all the days of my life.
看來以色列找到一位勇士了
Israel has found a champion.
別浪費我時間  小伙子
Don't waste my time, little boy.
你現在死還太年輕了
You're too young to die.
我要和你戰鬥
I will fight you.
父親  他成功了  大衛成功了
Father, he did it. David did it.
去抓奴隸吧
Let us make slaves of them!
大衛
David!
勇猛的牧羊英雄
My wolf in shepherd's clothing.
你挽救了我的王國  牧羊人勇士
You've saved my kingdom, my shepherd warrior!
跟我來  兄弟
Come with me, brother.
大衛加入了掃羅的軍隊
David joins Saul's army...
與非利士人打了幾十年的仗
and battles the Philistines for decades.
他成了一名勇士
He becomes a warrior,
一位領袖
a leader,
一個英雄
a hero.
掃羅  掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
掃羅殺敵數千
Saul has killed thousands!
掃羅  掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul!
掃羅  掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
你聽到了嗎  父親
You hear that, Father?
我聽到了
I hear.
掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul!
掃羅  掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
大衛殺敵萬萬
David has killed tens of thousands!
大衛  大衛
David! David!
大衛  大衛   大衛
David! David! David!
大衛  大衛   他理應得到他們的贊譽
David! David! He deserves their praise.
接下來他就該覬覦我的王位了
He'll want my crown next.
大衛  大衛
David! David!
我以為你當時摔下馬了
I thought you were going to fall off your horse.
是摔下了馬
I did fall off my horse.
我摔下來的時候還壓死了一個人
I think I killed a man when I landed on him.
一度我看見兩個男人站在我面前
There was one point there were two men in front of me.
大衛
David.
過來
Come here.
所以..
So,
你又一次成了我們的英雄
once again, you are our champion.
你殺敵數千
You have killed thousands.
數萬呢
Tens of thousands.
當然
Of course.
數萬人
Tens of thousands.
我們的人民都非常感激你
Our people are very grateful to you.
上帝保佑我們所有人
The Lord blessed us all.
我要獎賞你
I would like to reward you.
我把我的女兒米甲許配給你
I offer you my daughter, Michal.
我深感榮幸  陛下
I'm very honoured, Majesty.
大衛  我們現在是兄弟了
David, we're brothers now.
作為回報
In return...
我要一百條非利士人的性命
100 dead Philistines.
你怎麼看
Hmm? What say you?
一百個非利士人  由你手刃
100 dead Philistines slain by your own hand.
父親
Father,
他以身犯險的還不夠嗎
he's risked his life enough, no?
如果他回不來怎麼辦
What if he doesn't return?
我會回來的
I shall return.
如上果帝許可
God willing.
你愛他如親兄弟一般吧
You love him like a brother, don't you?
是啊
I do.
就像亞伯曾經愛戴該隱一樣
As Abel, no doubt, once loved Cain.
他覬覦我們的王位
He wants our crown.
你看不出來嗎   不
Can't you see? No.
他忠於我們   胡說
He's loyal to us both. Nonsense!
給您帶了點紀念品
A few mementos for you.
還有這些
And these.
從每具屍體上拿回來的戰利品
Trophies taken from each of their bodies.
一百具屍體嗎
From a hundred men?
兩百具
200.
上帝與我同在
God was with me.
米甲
Michal.
我們走吧
Let's go.
出去   所有人
Get out, all of you.
滾出去
Get out!
父親
Father.
是什麼魔鬼蒙蔽了你
What demons possess you?
如果不是因為他   我們都會變成奴隸
If it wasn't for him, we would all be slaves...
你也不會繼續當王
and you would not be king.
但有了他  你永遠不會成為王
And with him, you never will be.
你父親  也就是王  想見大衛
Your father, the king,wishes to see David.
不行  他現在...身體不適
He can't. He's... not well.
身體不適
Not well!
你是說"身體不適"嗎
Not well, you say.
我們來瞧瞧  來瞧瞧
Well- Well, we shall see.
來瞧瞧
We shall see.
身體不適
Not well.
大衛
David?
好啊
Yes.
幹得好啊
你幫他逃跑了
You have helped him escape.
比起你父親的王位  你更在意自己的後位   不
You would rather be queen than see your own father king! No!
你背叛了自己的兄長
You would betray your own brother!
父親  您需要休息
Father, you need to rest!
連我的親生孩子都算計我
So... even my own children plot against me!
大衛
David!
不論你逃到何方  我都饒不了你
Wherever you go, I shall hunt you down!
祭司
Priests!
你們的王有話要問你
Your king wishes to speak with you.
出來  -快出來
- Come here! Out! - Come on!
大衛曾來過  對不對
David was here, wasn't he?
你們為他提供了庇護   這裡是聖殿
You sheltered him. This is God's house.
我們為所有上帝的子民提供庇護
We offer shelter to all his people.
殺了他
Kill him.
我說殺了他
I said kill him!
全部殺掉
Kill all of them.
我忠心地侍奉您  耶和華
I have served you faithfully, Lord.
盡我所能  全心全意
As faithfully as a man can.
但如今看來  似乎依然不夠
And yet still it seems it is not enough.
永遠不夠
Not enough.
上帝與我同在
God is with me!
主啊
Lord!
您聽見你的僕人嗎？
Do you hear your servant?
陛下
Majesty...
大衛
David.
我並未傷害過您  您為何對我窮追不舍
Why do you pursue me when I have done you no harm?
我剛剛本可以殺了你
I could have killed you.
取你性命  易如反掌
Your life was mine to take.
那你為何沒有下手
Why didn't you take it then?
主自會懲罰你對我犯下的罪孽
The Lord may revenge the harm you have done to me,
但惡事出於惡人
but only evildoers do evil deeds.
我卻不加害於你
So my hand will not touch you. Ever.
可是上帝會賞賜你  你將成為王
And God will reward you,and you will be king!
您才是我的王   輪到你當王了
You are my king. And when you have my crown,
你難道不會剪除我的後裔？   不會讓我臭名？
will you not kill my descendants, bury my name?
我不會   不會嗎
I will not. No?
我發誓
I swear.
不會嗎
No?
那你過來
Come then.
過來
Come.
我們一起回家
We'll go home together.
你當時為何不趁機殺了他
Why did you not kill him when you had the chance?
因為他也是受膏者之一
Because he's one of the anointed.
唯有上帝才能決定他的命運
It's up to God to decide his destiny.
父親
Father!
Father.
父親
非利士軍隊駐扎在基利波附近的山谷
The Philistine army is in the next valley, near Gilboa.
約拿單  大衛可能會暗算我們
Jonathan, David is very near.
別再想大衛了
Forget about David.
你必須保衛自己的王國
You must defend your kingdom.
這是你的職責
That is your duty.
你說得對
You're right.
我們必須備戰
We must prepare for battle.
告訴軍隊  我們要朝基利波進發
Tell the men we leave for Gilboa.
破曉就出發
Tell them we leave at dawn.
約拿單  別管我了
Jonathan, save yourself!
不  我們要並肩作戰
No! We stand together!
父親  快走  快走
Father, come on! Come on!
拉弓
Draw!
約拿單
Jonathan!
約拿單   約拿單
Jonathan. Jonathan.
不  我兒
Oh, my son!
不  為什麼
Oh, why?
親愛的主啊
Dear God.
是否因我罪孽深重
Were my sins so great...
所以整個以色列都要受苦受難
all of Israel must suffer?
駕  駕
Hyah! Hyah!
非利士人
A crushing victory...
大獲全勝
for the Philistines.
掃羅呢
And Saul?
死了
Dead.
你認為上帝的受膏者身亡不值一提嗎
You think the death of God's anointed is a trivial thing?
約拿單呢
What of Jonathan?
被俘了嗎
Captured?
殺了他
Get rid of him!
一代偉人竟這般逝去
How are the mighty fallen.
我們可以回家
We can go home.
現在人民只能指望你了
The people will look to you now...
抵御外敵  凝聚人心
to defend them, unite them.
是時候了
Our time has come.
是的  我的陛下
Yes, my king.
大衛王
King David.
大衛召集了追隨者
David gathers followers.
但想團結以色列百姓  還需城池來建都
But to unite Israel, he needs a capital city.
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem.
我們的新家園
Our new home.
只要想出辦法進城就可以了
Now we just need to find a way in.
如何進城
How do we do that?
只有一個法子
There is one way.
等待夜幕的降臨
We wait till nightfall.
現在怎麼辦
What do we do now?
拿著
Here.
掃羅發生了什麼事
...what happened to Saul!
為了以色列
For Israel.
小心  -拿起武器
Look out! To arms!
烏利亞
Uriah!
以色列
Israel!
耶路撒冷城現在是大衛的都城了
Jerusalem is now David's city,
這座城市成為以色列人新的權力中心
a new center of power for the Israelites...
也是他們信仰上帝的終極象徵
and a home for the ultimate symbol of their bond with God.
約櫃
The Ark of the Covenant!
我的朋友  你妻子太漂亮了
Your wife's far too pretty for you, my friend.
沒錯
You're right.
陛下   來
Majesty. Come.
你不介意吧  烏利亞  -可我介意
You don't mind, Uriah. I mind.
如今上帝才真正與我同在了
Now God is truly with me.
陛下
Your Majesty.
先知
Ah. Prophet.
看
Look.
這是我獻給
My temple.
約櫃的聖殿
For the Ark.
也獻給主
For the Lord.
這會是世上獨一無二的聖殿
The world's never seen anything like it.
主昨晚降臨
The Lord came to me last night.
他對我們的工作很滿意吧
He's pleased with our work?
主示說  大衛家將永遠統治以色列
The Lord told me the House of David will rule Israel forever.
我們深蒙神寵
We are blessed.
你的兒子將續位為王
Your son will be king.
你的兒子會建造聖殿
Your son will build the temple.
我的聖殿
My temple.
主的聖殿
God's temple.
永恆之國
A kingdom forever.
謝謝你  拿單
Thank you, Nathan.
陛下
Your Majesty.
如您所要求
As you requested.
退下吧
Leave us.
拔示巴
Bathsheba.
陛下
Majesty...
叫我大衛吧
David.
可有我丈夫的音訊
Is there news of my husband?
沒有
No.
不不  這並非噩耗   雖然遠在千裡之外
No, nothing like that. He's safe enough, I believe,
但我相信他應該平安無恙
although he is far away.
抵御外敵
Fighting the enemy.
但您卻沒有上戰場
But you didn't go.
我不用去
No need.
因為有烏利亞這樣的勇士替我去
Not with men like Uriah to do it for me.
我忠於我的丈夫
I am loyal to my husband.
那對你的王呢
What about your king?
這是不對的
This is wrong.
無人會知曉
No one need know.
後來  拔示巴懷孕了
Bathsheba becomes pregnant.
上帝選中的王違背了他的誡命
God's chosen king breaks his commandments.
烏利亞  我的朋友  歡迎
Uriah, my friend. Welcome.
您找我嗎  殿下
You sent for me, Majesty.
戰況如何
How's the war going?
挺好的  很順利
Well. Very well.
你的統領官約押  他一切都好嗎
And your commander, Joab, all is well with him?
都很好
All is well.
其他士兵呢
Your fellow soldiers?
征戰英勇
They fight well.
非常好
Excellent.
你可以明早再來向我詳細匯報
Well, you can give me a fuller report in the morning.
我想你現在一定很想和妻子在一起
I'm sure for now you'd rather be with your wife.
我不能去找我的妻子  -當然可以
I cannot stay with my wife. Of course you can.
可我的士兵們還駐扎在野外
While my men are camped in open country,
與敵人激戰
fighting the enemy?
這是一場聖戰
This is a holy war.
我怎麼可以回家  與妻子共度良宵
How could I go to my home and spend the night with my wife?
所以你這麼受人愛戴  烏利亞
That does you credit, Uriah.
但是說實在的
But, man to man,
誰會知道這事
who's to know?
我自己心知肚明
I will know.
正直之士啊
Good man.
讓我們開懷暢飲吧
Then let's drink.
上酒
Wine!
大衛無法迫使烏利亞與拔示巴同床
David cannot force Uriah to sleep with Bathsheba.
所以他另覓他法
So he finds another way...
來掩蓋通奸之事
to conceal his adultery.
約押將軍  我命令你派遣烏利亞
Commander Joab,I order you to send Uriah...
去到陣勢極險之處
to where the fighting is fiercest...
丟下他  令其自生自滅
and abandon him there to die.
我們真是福澤深厚
We've been richly blessed.
你以為可以掩蓋自己所做的事嗎
You think you can just sweep what you've done under the carpet?
你奪走了你最忠誠的僕人烏利亞的一切
You took everything from your most loyal servant, Uriah.
你本該敬重他才是  -我確實尊重他
He deserved your respect. I did respect him.
是嗎
Really?
你奪人妻子  然後又害死了他   先知
You took his wife, then you took his life. Prophet!
你以為上帝對此一無所知嗎
You think God doesn't see everything?
上帝已經對我說了
The Lord has spoken to me.
由於你蔑視上帝
He will bring disaster on your house...
他將讓你一家蒙受災難
for the contempt you have shown the Lord.
不  -不
- No. - No!
他將拿去你的兒子
He will take your son.
我們走著瞧
We shall see.
主啊  我願奉獻一切
Anything, Lord.
請饒過吾兒吧
Please spare my child.
請告訴我
Tell me.
告訴我該做什麼
Tell me what to do.
哦
Oh.
先是我丈夫  現在是我的孩子
First my husband, now my son.
我們被咒詛了
We are cursed.
但我是受膏者
But I was anointed.
上帝賜福於我
God blessed me.
王永遠不可能超越上帝
A king is never above his god.
你本應以祂之名治理國家  而不是為你一己私欲
You were supposed to rule in his name, not your own.
我們完了
We're finished.
所有人都會看出  上帝已經拋棄了我們
Everyone will see that God has left us.
先知
Prophet.
雖然你意志薄弱  他依然愛你  大衛
Even though you are weak, he loves you, David.
你在人間建立了上帝的國度
You have forged God's nation on earth.
相互慰藉吧
Take comfort in each other.
你們還會有兒子的
You will have another son.
小心  所羅門
Be careful, Solomon.
讓他玩吧
Let him play.
這是聖殿
It's the house of the Lord.
總有一天  他要建立聖殿
One day, he'll have to build it.
所羅門會建造聖殿
Solomon will build God's temple.
但如他父親一般
But like his father,
他會發現  遵守上帝的誡命難於登天
he will find it impossible to obey God's commandments.
下集《聖經》預告
Next time on The Bible.
尼布甲尼撒  尼布甲尼撒
Nebuchadnezzar! Nebuchadnezzar!
上帝將從巴比倫帶來災難
God is bringing disaster from Babylon!
尼布甲尼撒
Nebuchadnezzar!
我們前進
We move!
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
你不向上帝傳達我們需要幫助嗎
Will you not speak for us in our hour of need?
看看外面
Look out there.
為時已晚
You're too late.
戰爭開始了
It begins.
臣服於尼布甲尼撒王   向他跪拜
Submit to King Nebuchadnezzar. Bow your head.
不管耶路撒冷還剩下什麼   隨你們處置
And whatever is left of Jerusalem, help yourselves!
這邊走  但以理
This way, Daniel.
我們還會回到耶路撒冷嗎
Will we ever return to Jerusalem?
耶利米保證過... 終有一天我們會的
Jeremiah promised that one day we would.
到那時  我們該怎麼做
In the meantime, what do we do...
對這個暴君俯首稱臣嗎
just bow our heads and serve this monster?
我會讓他們臣服的
I will make them bow.
給我點火
Bring me fire!
耶和華  救我
Lord! Save me!
如果預言是正確的  那麼古列會釋放我們
Cyrus will set us free if the prophecy is right.
我不能言而無信
I cannot go back on my word.
我已承諾人民信仰自由
I promised them freedom to worship.
這只是考驗他們的忠誠而已
It is merely a test of their loyalty.
這是個圈套  他們想置我們於死地
It's a trap for all of us. They want us dead.
將來的那一位  他將用火來施洗
There is one to come who will baptise with fire.
我不過是曠野中的吶喊   做好準備    迎接
I'm just a voice in the wilderness,preparing the way for the...
主
Lord.
我們要做什麼
What are we gonna do?
改變世界
Change the world.